這場活動我先介紹一下
因為有些現場是之前沒有來參加過的
我們這個健康網絡工作坊的系列是
由Jonas 索諾迪卡的組成
他在去年底的時候提出來一個想法
他就是把大家常常會遇到的問題
先做一些基本整理之後
他把常見的分類的問題
就是一項一項弄成一個大章節
然後一段一段來講
如果大家有先去看他Vtopper
的Republic of Greece上面的話
你會發現已經有一些更多的議題
已經在後面有在草稿籌劃當中
那就是說這個系列應該會持續辦下去
這個系列的問題不是為了解決單一的技術困難
或是針對性的問題
是針對一個比較共通的模式
去挑一些問題出來解
所以我們第一次在去年底辦了DeCoupling的講座
第二場在那時間點整理資料之後
CI是比較適合的下一場
所以就在這邊舉辦這一場
Continuous Integration 持續整合的講座
我們這個議程會用
偶爾會用國語翻譯
我會盡量帶國語翻譯的內容
不會到百分之百完全對應
因為很多技術細節
我這邊也沒辦法做百分之百的口語翻譯
如果有不明白
或是哪裡不清楚的地方
歡迎隨時舉手提出來
請講師再重新解釋
或是請我這邊再重新翻譯一次
都可以
因為要同時講雙語的關係
這場內容其實步調比較慢
如果你已經是CI有經驗的開發者的話
可能你可以在比較空間
如果你覺得這個MEME比較低
比較空的話
現在可以準備一些比較進階的問題
等一下可以問請問有哪些問題
好,所以我要重複一次
所以
For those who don't know about the Game Dev Workshop,
this healthy coding workshop,
Jonas started since last year, late last year, 2019.
He is the lead programmer on Subnautica,
which is a very hot game on Steam and other platforms.
Are you ready right now?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Xbox, PlayStation, Epic Games, Discord.
Windows Store.
Yeah, so.
Arc in China.
Okay, that's new.
Okay, so.
Yeah, so he noticed there are like just patterns
about like different type of questions within the game community that
we just constantly ask each other about.
And so the first session, the first workshop that he did was on decoupling.
So like how to go about just tidy your code base and then just make your code structure more clean and more maintainable.
And now the second topic this time, which is the thing we're doing right now, is on continuous integration.
which we'll be talking about Jenkins mainly,
and how Jenkins works with GitHub.
So if you have any advanced questions that you already,
maybe you're already a CI practitioner,
you're already a Jenkins user,
if you have any advanced questions
that you think our pacing's too slow,
just prepare your advanced questions
and ask us afterwards.
So, like, without further ado, so.
Let's give applause to Jens.
Thank you. Thank you all for coming, full house today.
Thank you for the introduction.
You already mentioned, we're mainly going to talk about Jenkins today, but let me ask.
So, continuous integration is one of the things that came up a lot in the feedback and suggestions document that I made.
所以在這方面,誰已經使用了一些類似的連接方式
有人想回答嗎?
如果你已經有使用持續整合的方法
在開發你的軟體或遊戲
那就可以選擇了
不過剛剛看起來大部分都聽得懂
我的目標是在今天工作結束後
all of you can know how to set this up and get it running.
It's not too hard if you know what you're doing.
The reason why I think this is useful to have is because
it's quite common to have something like this,
where someone changed something and now...
materials is missing
and you don't know
your game looks like this
and you don't know why
ok, so sorry
今天的目的就是希望說大家在
還沒有用過CI的人可能在進入之後
可以至少知道setup jankies
那今天這個
talker 最主要的常見的病因
就是像現在畫面中看到這個畫面
可能團隊裡面的某位美術或其他的
可能改了一下材質
然後材質就變成預設的
就變成紅色這樣就淘掉了
那這個狀況就是在沒有使用
持續審核的時候就很容易
不知道去哪裡抓是誰改的
Some programmer checks something in and now the code is not compiling.
Now everyone on the team cannot play the game and see how it runs.
So the idea would be to work separately from the main branch.
Say this is the main branch and the time goes in the right direction.
Branch off, do your task, work on it, and eventually you say,
OK, I'm ready to merge back to main.
But before you do that, you run an automated test
that verifies that you didn't actually break anything.
有在用Fargo管理的人應該都對這張圖不會太陌生
如果你要做新功能,還是你要加新東西
你應該自己開一個新的branch
然後branch就是分支
在你自己的電腦上確定可以執行,測試都過了
沒有其他奇怪的問題發現
你才會把你的分支merge回主要的那條主線裡面
So instead of merging this yourself, you would press a button somewhere and then an automated process would start.
And when it comes back everything green, then it would automatically merge it for you. You don't have to press anything anymore.
那理想的狀況就是說你在做merge之前
應該就要用類似像這樣的工具
去跑完所有的測試跟建置流程
自動跑完這個程序之後確定沒問題
你才去把它merge回去
就不用手動做這件事情
另一個我們可以自動化的地方是
當你做建築的時候
你可能會想要推廣到玩家、測試者
even your internal team.
So you have to make these builds for all the platforms that you support
and then upload them to whatever store it is
and you can also automate that.
另外一個可以自動化的部分就是
你在確定你的Build沒有問題之後
但你還是要給真人去玩
這個真人可能是在你團隊裡面的測試員
或是說其他的Beta的玩家
或是其他不同平台的玩家
送到不同的地方或不同的平台上去
這件事情也是可以被自動化的
所以比如說在Subnautica的過程中
我們有5,000個Build上載到Steam
他們都在Valve的伺服器上
如果你想再回到某個版本,你都可以
這個畫面就是Starmulio的Steam Build過去曾經送給松巴的經歷
Steam 裡面會把所有你送過的版本都保留一份下來
所以如果你發現任何問題
你可以隨時退回其中某一個版本
這有點太複雜了
像是推薦到Xbox或PlayStation
或其他商店因為他們有些手動步驟
但Steam 我們可以自行自行自行
這非常好
你不會有討論
例如它在我的機器上運作
但它在你的機器上運作,那有什麼問題呢?
這是大家可以玩的建築
其他非Steam的平台
中間可能會有一些手動程序
但是Steam的部分是可以完全自動化的
以上就是為什麼不斷進行的組合是一個好主意
有些問題可能你也有考慮過
所以在講座後,我會很高興回答你的問題
我們會嗎?
剛剛這樣子
大概講述的用途是
常見的CI使用情境
如果你有想到其他的情況
或是你覺得你其實
If you have similar needs in other fields,
you can come to us after today's session
and talk to him.
And so, in the survey,
what you want me to talk about,
I also asked like
who's using version control already
and it turns out basically everyone is using
some form of version control.
Lots of people are using GitHub.
This example is for the use case.
I'm more familiar with plastic, which is this thing,
but at the end of the day, it really doesn't matter.
We can make Jenkins talk to any version control system.
在Jonas去年發的問卷裡面
絕大部分的人對
版本控制這個概念
或是說版本控制相關的工具
其實都已經有在使用或是已經相當熟悉了
那這絕大部分應該是用Git
所以今天講的內容是Jankie's跟Git的配合
Jonas自己是用
工作上的商業方案是用Plastic MC
不過他講到說,Plexi XEM跟KIT基本上
到最後目的都一樣,用法其實也相當接近
概念都是相當接近
JAMming是可以跟各種不同的辦公系統配合
所以應該不會有什麼問題
OK, so how it works is
you want to have some sort of built-in
that can be just an old laptop or computer or something that you have
Preferably not your own machine because you want to have that run in Unity and not affect
your own work, not make your own PC slow.
But if you can't have your own machine and run it overnight, it's also fine.
在安裝Streaming之前
或是開始做今天workshop內容之前
最好找一台空電腦或舊電腦
現在已經沒有正式在使用的來安裝比較適合
因為基本上這個東西會一直在背景執行
如果你平常要用那台電腦的話
它會在背景裡面一直定期跑
這樣對你應該會造成蠻多的困擾
所以通常
需要自動化的建設流程的時候
都是會另外找一台專用機器
就算是舊的也沒關係
總之它是整理過比較乾淨的
我順便再補充一下
現在畫面上看到的是英文版本的Docker資料
但是如果你去Docker的話
它下面都有翻譯連結
現在翻譯中的翻譯
是在同樣的Repository裡面可以看到
所以如果你有現在在開Docker的話
可以直接去看翻譯中的翻譯
Right, so you have a computer, you install Jenkins, that's fairly straightforward.
There's a Windows installer, it's linked in the project here.
And once you've installed Jenkins on your machine, you go to localhost 8080.
Where is it? Yeah, localhost 8080.
What you see is this, right?
Jenkins 的安裝連結在這個頁面上
我們有放一個超頁解構過去
基本上就是把板子做一系統用的版本
抓下來然後執行
拋下來之後會是一個在你電腦上配置執行的Server
它的Server 經常開在Logos上面
Port 現在是8080
所以如果你現在切到Logos的Tab
如果你正常安裝好之後
你的 Jenkins 應該就會正常拋下來
如果你想繼續,可以下載並安裝現在
不用擔心無法安裝
很容易刪除檔案,沒有缺口
如果想直接測試,之前沒有用過的話
可以直接到 GitHub 連結下載到其他裝置
到時候要砍掉的話很簡單,砍掉資料再直接砍就好
OK,所以我們把它安裝好
我們想要創造新的工作
給它名字
或是工作
選擇Pipeline Project
因為Pipeline是
我們最有控制的
在他建立新工作的介面裡面
就選擇輸入他們的專案名稱
就是工作名稱之後我們就選Pipeline這個選項
Pipeline通常在實際實戰上面之後最常用到
然後你的控制權也比較多的一個選項
There's a lot of stuff to configure
We're going to ignore all that
It's not very important
What really is important is this
We want a pipeline script from the version control system
這是Git的管理系統
在設定預設的工作樣板之後
上面很多打工的選項
絕大部分在
現在常用的專案大部分是不重要的
可以先跳過,先把專案跑起來比較重要
先把工作跑起來比較重要
唯一的關鍵是我們現在是要跑Pipeline的腳本
而且是要從版本控制的資料夾裡面
去跑Pipeline檔案
So if you're using a GitHub desktop or anything GitHub, you already know how to get the repository URL.
I think it's somewhere here.
Yeah, this URL. Take that.
Put it over here.
我用的是公開的資料庫,所以我不需要有登入
如果是私人資料庫,可以直接輸入
你自己的DATE儲存庫裡面
就把DATE檔的UIL
複製技能就好了
如果你的Git是公開的
就不用設任何Credential
也不用設任何帳號密碼
但如果是私人的Git server
帳號密碼就自己設定
目前還是展示
在這個Workshop資料庫的資料夾裡面
有的不只是Readme說明
是連Unity的翻譯專案
跟Jankins的翻譯專案
都在裡面
所以是完全Follow這個
In the workshop, you can go to the GitHub repository of the workshop prepared by Jonas.
You can find the corresponding files directly on GitHub.
In my project, I've already put a Janus file into the repository.
It looks roughly like this and what I would recommend to you is just copy it because all
you have to do is change these things to whatever you're using on your machine but then the
rest of the script is always the same.
建議如果你要直接使用Workshop的內容
這個版本的Jetkins設定的話
直接把這個檔案的內容全部複製下來就可以了
唯一要修改的部分是前面的環境
執行環境與發問的部分
你的Git或是你的應用體可能掛在不一樣的地方
或是你的抓謎程度不一樣
前面那些可能要稍微仔細設定一下
它上面還有預設Steam的
帳號密碼或是說Stream的目錄
或者是如果你今天是要發佈到其他不同平台
一些相關東西,那個變數名稱等於自己要加
下面那些Stage
就是下面的整個Jetkins的執行流程
基本上不變
OK, so I put this in here, that in there
And that's basically it, let's try it, if it works
剛剛把這東西設置起來之後,它應該就可以自動跑了
So the good news is, I found the Jenkins file.
The path is correct, the repository is correct.
And while this is going,
we can look at the log file.
左邊是Pipeline
是指個人的步驟
右邊是建立程序的操作輸出
所有的須要的程序
對,因為JAMMIN是直接跑一個伺服器在你的本機上
或是你到處找一個專用的機器
它就是跑一台伺服器專門去做這件事情
在伺服器上跑的操作資訊
就是它在建立的過程中會出現所有的通知訊息
and the alarm will be sent immediately.
The steps you see on the left, you can go down step by step.
Time will go down slowly.
If the log is actually jumping out from the side,
you can open the log's monitor window,
and it will jump out.
So you normally don't see this stuff.
This is a Unity output that goes into an editor log file
somewhere deep in your system.
But for the build process,
we're redirecting it to Jenkins
so that we can see live what the build server is doing.
Even when we're...
不是在機器上的實際情況
如果你在網路上,與我的機器連接
或是8080
你會看到這個
這個東西就是平常你自己在用Munity
建制專案或是測試專案的時候
本來就會跑一些log跟資訊
通常這個東西可能大部分都會被影響起來
在 Jenkins 這邊,他把所有的刻意備忘錄下來
全部都 Redirect 出來到這個 server 的 console 界面上
如果你現在可以直接連到 local IP 的 body line
直接對聯到這段式的 server 上
應該可以看到相關的資訊在這裡
其實可以試試看
大家可以連接到 SIP 4888
也許我有些檔案會失去
如果有人想要測試的話可以給他們看192.168.102.33
8080不知道會看到什麼
如果沒有用的話給我一個讚
我會繼續測試
總之現在就是要等它跑完
如果有人想要花幾秒鐘試一下
可以試看看
不過我還有
線跟無線網路的區段沒有存檯
所以我不知道
Oh, I forgot one thing. When you go to that website, 8080, you are asked to log in.
The Jenkins installation process says your initial Jenkins password is in this file
and your Jenkins installation secrets initial admin password.
So you can copy it from there.
如果你之前有用過GemCache的話
現在才安裝的話
你會發現第一次跑伺服器的時候
伺服器會叫你去找一個預設生成密碼
你要先把預設生成密碼填進去
在你本機上網的位置
它在Store的畫面上會跟你講
你就是把那個密碼貼進去之後才能開始正式安裝過程
看來我們很幸運
一切都成功了
最長的程度是
for the project to get imported
the import asset step in Unity
where it's actually the progress bar
and then to actually build a stand-alone executable
and then this last step where it would upload to Steam
that's just fake right now
it's not actually uploading anything to anywhere
Let's have a look at the Jenkins file
剛剛Jonas講說
會跑比較久的幾個步驟,其中一個是Import Session
Import Session那邊是
你在硬體開作案起來的時候
如果是重新開一次的話
它都會有一些像Package之類的Import程序
那個東西就是JKX會真的去跑這個東西
然後真的去做單元測試
然後真的去做建置
然後建置完之後就會有真正可以用的執行檔
那執行檔如果你是在本機
設定你的Jetkins Server的話
它就會存在你本機本網的部分
可能是在Jetkins的相關資料夾裡面
最後一步驟
它剛剛的UploadView其實有跑完
但是如果現在看到右邊的畫面的話
那個Stage UploadView的那邊
那段指令目前是沒有作用的
就是它的Steam指令跟Steam的帳號密碼當然是假的
你可以看到上面
它現在是用假的SteamUserName跟SteamPassword
所以當然什麼都沒有說
If you want to use it, you can go from the upload view,
you can automatically upload it to the specified format.
But we're not done. That's out of the scope for today. If you have questions about that, we can do another workshop for that.
Now, I said that...
One of the main reasons why we're doing all this is because we want to prevent this from happening.
We want to detect that something broke.
To do that, what we're actually doing in the script is we run the unit test.
Running the unit test looks like...
所以我們剛剛講到說
到底會不會看我們剛剛做的範例流程
為什麼要做這麼多事情
那就是回到最開始講的
我們想要避免那種莫名其妙材質跑掉
還是說什麼東西突然間不能扛太好的狀況
那這在多人合作的時候很容易發生
那要防止這樣的情況出現
除了把你剛剛的 Jenkins 這樣建立建置好之外
最重要的其實是要考裡面那個單元測試的步驟
Luckily, Unity has a function.
You can start Unity from the command line and say, if you
run unit test, it works.
Here we say, build a player.
And it does the right thing.
And if the unit test had any problem, then this
build step would fail.
Let's try to create a problem and see if that fails.
Unity的Command Line命令列的操作模式
是可以下不同的參數
你可以下現在只是要run editor的測試
或是你現在要run特定的不同的階段
還是你要真的build最後的版本
你可以下不同的參數去決定
目前就是Jonas想要試一下
如果我故意把這個狀況改爛
那看它有沒有真的在Unity testing的階段會掛掉
如果他不喜歡,網路應用程式會改變
所以我不會用我的專業能力來做這個演講
我們來看看會不會成功
這個問題是大中華區獨有的問題
坐在這邊有在用的應該都知道
就是你的個人版的證書
每過七天就要去重新按一次
如果你BTFB它跳進去的話
結果可以採Portable
那就麻煩了
Give it a little moment
Yes, question
Can you enlarge the front?
It's a bit hard to see
Sorry, I cannot hear you
No, can you enlarge the front?
Make it bigger
Probably the easiest would be
No, I shouldn't do that, right?
I shouldn't change the resolution
And the stream breaks and stuff?
No, I'm not doing it.
Sorry.
But if you're on the browser, you can just control path here.
Yeah.
Yeah, this is a good idea.
Yeah, apologies if it's a little bit small, I think.
Are we going to record the stream?
Yeah.
Yeah, so you can re-watch it on YouTube or something.
If any of this is too small.
In Unity I cannot make it bigger, I'm sorry.
Okay, so we have in this project, in this demo project for this workshop,
I've put two unit tests in there.
One is...
It doesn't look like the latest version.
Aha, okay.
I have a generic test for asset bundles and a test for shaders.
We're going to destroy the test for asset bundles and see what happens.
So the test for asset bundles is...
The idea is basically, you have some materials...
When you put stuff in asset bundles,
you can run into a problem
where assets get duplicated.
我會展示這個,然後讓測試失敗
然後再建造一次
通過 Jenkins 看到建造流程停止
然後再跟我們報告,它不再運作
現在Translator要做一點測試S8的內容修改
呼,頭好暈
他說在XML常見的問題是
有時候材質或內容會莫名其妙的
在幾次變更之後自己複製一份
有時候這樣會造成一些衝突
他現在模擬一些類似的情況
如果故意做這樣的修改之後
是不是在Jenkins那邊自動review的過程
他就會自動fail那一刻
Okay, so let's say I have a few textures, and I have a few materials, and I set up a PVC.
Very simple.
And I put these materials into an asset bundle.
Like this.
So, portals.
Now I have an asset bundle, or I build an asset bundle with these three materials,
and because they reference these textures, those textures would also be packed into the asset bundle portals.
Who's using asset bundles yet?
It's just an example.
If I have another material,
also references the same texture and put that in a different asset bundle.
I don't know. So not again.
Now I have the same texture, which is this one, referenced in two different asset bundles,
and Unity gets very confused in which asset bundle this texture should get packed.
So it just packs it in both asset bundles, and now you have the same texture.
會在你的項目中重複一次
重複吃掉你的記憶體
這個特定問題是
他現在在示範的特定問題是說
它有三個貼圖裡面其中一個
被包含到兩個不同的SF方程
所以它A跟A2是在兩個不同的SF方程裡面
在這種情況下,硬體會有點混亂
基本上它會讓那個貼圖被
多複製一次到不同的SF方程裡面
你不能讀到,因為很小
它說這個質量,CoreLit 01,就是這個
是用兩個asset bundle來複製的,這不是一個好主意
總之就是現在他自己已經偵測到
Fuzion Asset的Duplicate
就是Asset他自己被複製了一份
那這邊在他的Test Run的時床裡面
已經有出現警告訊息
我們現在來檢查示範中
現在把這個實際上目前確實是有初期版本
直接送到Git
就是你的Git server上面
然後我們就看看
因為剛剛的檢評是他的檔案
裡面設定是說他要直接去GitHub上面
這個專案拉下來去檢視試器
所以我們剛剛做完這些假的模擬抽的操作之後
我們要假裝把它放上去
抽管放上去之後
就看看是不是等一下在檢視裡面會出錯
OK, now everything is on here
and if we fail
the project that we just made.
This one workshop.
A little bit.
Let's have a look.
Got it?
Tickets use a different workspace and it's not the same workspace that I just opened.
It's downloading the stuff there and it's importing the assets there.
At least I hope it does.
Like I said, I'm mostly using plastic, so I'm not 100% sure that I'm getting this, that it gets things right with like...
Set, check out...
I think it should work.
Oh yeah, I've got some of the textures already.
So it's done importing the assets.
Now it's starting Unity again and running the unit test.
Aha! Beautiful.
As you can see on the left side, it failed.
然後運行UnityX
所以剛剛看到的是
UnityX在單元測試裡面確實有出現錯誤
然後過程就暫緩
在這面出現錯誤的時候
它可以直接跳到有錯誤的部分
這樣就可以檢查出錯,到底哪邊出錯
supposed to say a little bit nicer what failed in the log file, so that tells you, okay, what
exactly broke. I'm not finding it right now, but it's there somewhere. And that's good
enough for now, I think.
Jemmy的錯誤訊息,跳出去有點長
如果有compile error,還是像剛剛那樣sfbundle的錯誤
可能要花點時間才能找到錯誤在哪邊
但一般注意到一個錯誤,或是一個常見的錯誤
理論上那個錯誤的關鍵字應該是
你自己會有印象,或者是說你可以直接搜尋特定的時距
然後就直接去看有沒有這個錯誤出現
我應該要提醒大家,如果任何一個步驟失敗,其他步驟也不會被執行
一般來說,這步驟只需要一分鐘,但現在只需要一秒鐘
所以這步驟是跳過其他步驟
所以如果你的雲端是好的,你不會上載一張被破壞的電腦,這很棒
如果說剛在Intel的錯誤掛掉的話
它Build那邊雖然還是有跑時間
不過你可以注意到它的時間比剛剛成功的時候是短很多的
原因就是因為它Build那段時間的效果
它是跑一些基本流程
那個時間搞不好是因為它要輸出各種Company Line的資訊
所以才會有那個時間差距
但基本上它是沒有真的執行到建置跟上傳的部分
Yep, that's all the questions
基本上就是今天展示的部分大概就到這邊
你可以看到我們成功的跑完一次
然後我們改了錯誤的東西
就假裝好像真的是不小心改錯的東西
進到自己的專案裡面
然後這樣真的在跑
確實也是它會跳錯誤出來
Let's see if anyone has any questions after this.
You can ask now.
So actually I would just ask a question directly.
Because I noticed that when you were showcasing the SFBundle errors,
that SFBundle error showed up in, like, whoever was editing that SFBundle,
that's...
that person should already know this is an error.
Right?
Like this error here.
Basically, he knows if he actually saves this file, and
then he actually builds an asset bundle here, he will
know that this is an error.
Then under what kind of situation would this kind of
error slip into the main repository?
Right.
There are some errors that are just stupid and shouldn't really slip if everyone was doing the job properly.
And then there are some errors that are really difficult.
Like, if I'm an artist and I'm replacing this texture or something,
and I'm not super careful to preserve the meta file, then it gets a different ID.
And something that references the texture, like this material,
and some other folder completely on the other side of the project,
would have a broken material.
It looks like I've deleted it,
and then this material here would be broken,
and then later in the game, you would see an error.
So just because you've changed something on this end,
can mean that something on that end breaks.
You've changed some code.
some part breaks, you change some parts and code breaks, really like completely separate disciplines
and it's very very difficult as the project grows to keep track of everything that could possibly
break and that's why it's important to have automation that gives you the confidence that
okay all the tests are green so at least I know that all of what we test didn't break.
你的問題是,你真的測試了所有東西嗎?
還是有些東西沒有被測試過?
我剛剛的問題是想說
以剛剛SFBundle的例子來說
在操作這個過程中的人
他應該在這個畫面就會看到
就是有抽搐出來
只是我是想說什麼情況下會造成
他真的把有錯誤的版本送到你的公台
或是說你的主要的Git的Server上面
剛剛這個例子其實是比較誇張的例子
他只是為了要趕快展示一下有錯誤的東西
然後執行出去之後
那JS執行真的會失敗
另外一個可能性,像剛剛那個貼圖不見的問題
那Title不見了會造成Unity就不能談話了
還是說它執行起來就馬上可以看到錯誤
因為搞不好畫面
它剛好錯誤的部分就沒有呈現在畫面上
你沒有辦法注意到哪個Title遺憲
那樣子的東西有可能是
A美術改了一個東西
然後B程式去拉新的版本下來
要更新美術固態的時候
就發現什麼東西壞掉還是消失了
這種情況下,你會需要寫更多的單元測試,去驗證有沒有類似的情況發生
所以最後的關鍵是,你要把你曾經看過的錯誤都納入單元測試裡面
至少你犯過一次的錯誤,透過自動化流程,讓你不會再犯第二次
So, two very useful tests for us on Subnautica that we have in our project is one test runs
across all the prefabs and checks all the components.
如果有任何不足的資訊
整個項目就要花半分鐘或兩分鐘
視乎你擁有多少資料
所以如果有任何問題
所以Jonas說他們在Sanonica正式的專案裡面
有兩個很有用的Dynamics測試
其中一個
第一個Dynamics測試就是說
它去檢查所有整個專案裡面有沒有
它的Material Element裡面有那種命名就變成Missing
就是很明顯它東西就是不見
那大概要花個半分鐘一分鐘去執行
才能考完整個專案裡面所有的這個元件
但是如果你找到的話就知道
它Discount有改錯了
所以它才會變成就是找不到素材或是找不到貼紙
找不到材質這樣
some field that other people have to fill out when they assign your component to a game object.
Like, okay, you know, this always has to get linked.
We have like an attribute which we slap on,
and then we have a test that runs across all the prefabs,
all the scripts, goes through all the fields in the script and checks.
所有的東西,當它有這樣的特徵
那麼這個必須在所有的prefab中被設定
另外一個,第二個測試,剛剛講到很有用的測試
他們有制定一個Unity的attribute
然後他把這個attribute都放在
那個元件的這些field前面
那他就是去檢查說到底
它有另外一個測試去跑說
所有有標上HPU的這些欄位
是不是真的都有填東西
因為它主要是它percent non-null
就是它要被檢查出來不是虛無值
表示說可能有人拉了就已經進來到新的場景裡面
它沒有被指定該被指定的東西
全部解答完之後,如果沒有問題,單元測試才會過
如果其中一個missing,還是no,就是不會過
所以這兩個測試並不建立在Unity,我們寫的那個是碼子
但我認為我可以重新寫,然後開放到我們的GitHub repository
然後你就可以使用它,所以並不太難
這兩個功能當然不是硬體內建的
所以他們是SmartKey這個團隊裡面自製的檢查
如果有必要的話,可以把這兩個很常見的檢查類型
直接check in到目前我們都不需要的資料夾裡面
如果有人想要看的話,可以直接看這個版本
你自己可以再修改成自己要的形式
Great.
Yeah, cool.
Thanks, Andrew.
Any more questions?
Do you want me to teach you?
Oh, sure.
So I'm a bit curious about how long does it take to fully test
and build some hardware in the CI environment
and how often you release the build to QA?
And how long does it take to point you to verify that this build is ready for release?
How often do we run it?
How long does the whole process run for Subnautica?
How long does it take for you to get the thing to QAT?
How long is the response time from QAT to and back?
Right, so our entire build process, all of this,
the unit tests and building for a project of the size of Subnautica
takes about 20 minutes.
Uploading to Steam takes longer or shorter depending on whether you change a lot or a little.
Steam is pretty clever.
And then, once it is on Steam, Steam distributes it automatically instantly to everyone who is on that branch.
So what we do is we have two branches.
So we have the default branch, which is what you play when you just home the product.
But then you can also opt in to an experimental branch.
It's a little bit small.
I don't know how to zoom in here.
Is this a Google slide?
That's a Google slide, yeah.
Yeah, I don't know.
You can go to Steam, you can press experimental and then you get the new build basically within 10 minutes or something of us pushing it to Steam.
So the entire cycle is less than an hour.
And because we push our builds to experimental and there's no password on it as you can tell, anyone can...
can play that if they want to.
That's a crazy idea because it's probably
like lots of stuff that isn't
100% working but
super easy for our
QA, for our playtesters
to always
play the latest build. It's very, very fast.
So the QA and
testers are basically
playing a public build, right?
Yeah.
You just log into that and it's basically a public build.
Yeah, exactly.
And when we think that the build, the experimental build, is good enough,
then we go in here and we click this button and say,
okay, now make this build live on the default branch.
So, click this one, select default, and then click okay.
And then that's how you...
發表這個規定給所有的玩家
因為這不是一個很簡單的規定
所以我會詳細的總結整個Q&A
所以就是
Telos 提到說在整個像Summoner's Rift這樣等級的遊戲
這樣的規模的遊戲裡面
大概
剛剛Jankx這樣從頭到尾七個步驟跑完
大概要20分鐘左右
上傳跟發佈的短時間
大約在10幾20分鐘之內
差不多是這個時間
整個流程
真的有真的可以玩到
剛剛Jankin跑完上傳的版本
應該是一小時之內
因為
SummerCat在Steam上有一個實驗的分支
這個實驗的分支是公開的,並沒有鎖
只要你願意當買家鎖的話
可以直接選擇這個分支來下載
他們自己的QA跟測試員也是用這個實驗分支
所以他就沒有另外一層
所謂的公司內QA專用的版本
還是公司內QA專用伺服器之類的
它是直接用Steam的公開功能去做這些事情
整個流程應該是說,你的JS開始跑,跑到結束
到Steam的CDN幫你發佈到所有可以下載的點
讓人家可以從Steam的界面上下載
這樣的過程應該是第一小時
整個專案的大小,就算是現在在跑
30G、38G、40G平均
It sounds very short for me.
It sounds short because our QA is complaining it's long.
But sometimes we have the programmer connect to the players just live,
and then they fix something and they basically want to play it again.
And then an hour is pretty long.
But Subnautica is also a very big project.
I'll let it count now, but I think it comes out at around 100 gigs.
So if you have a smaller project, the antithread process is much faster and you can have a turnaround of like 5 minutes.
Why are there 5,000 folders?
Oh?
Why are there 5,000 folders? What is the structure of that?
Probably Unity's library folder.
Oh.
It's only 60.
SolidWare的專案大小是60G
然後兩張20幾萬的檔案
這樣的專案規模去build下去
剛講的大概20分鐘可以在圈內上跑
不過我不想知道是不是在手機上會有
或是手機環境上會有比較多
莫名其妙的情況讓你的builder power cycle變長
是有遇到一些問題
We have a news about dual-screen BIOS.
He said there is a big mobile project in his company,
that if you build towards iOS and Android both,
it takes more than 14 hours to complete.
Okay.
That would be interesting to hear.
to know why, because if it's taking a long time to compile,
then you can use assembly definition files,
and if it's taking a long time to build the assets or package the assets,
that's something that you can actually cache and only rebuild the parts that need rebuilding.
So one thing that I didn't mention...
In the build pipeline that I showed you, I'm keeping the
library folder because otherwise every time I clean
everything, all the private files and everything, but I
keep the library folder because otherwise the next build
would have to reimport everything again.
So this helps a lot with big projects.
But then yeah, if you have asset funnels that are nicely packed,
you don't have to rebuild them over and over again unless something changes.
But it's difficult to say what exactly is it without profiling.
Yes?
I would ask you about scaling.
Like, if you have ever problems that you are making too many builds and too many people working on the projects,
and then like the pipeline kind of like stuck because with this approach you can only execute one pipeline at the same time.
Right.
So, have you tried to use some Docker for that or like more nodes or how do you feel?
The problem was can there ever be too many builds and...
And luckily that's a problem that you can always fix by adding more computers.
So right now I'm using Jenkins and the build server is the Jenkins server.
But in theory you can have lots of other computers and they can be Jenkins slaves.
So Jenkins tells them, okay, do this thing now, right?
And so if you have, if your build takes 30 minutes.
But within those 30 minutes, there are other builds that you also have to make or other unit tests that you also have to run.
As long as you have enough machines that you can handle those requests concurrently, then nothing clogs up.
If you don't have enough machines, then Jenkins just queues it and will work down the queue.
If it's not a 14-hour build, there's a very good chance that overnight everything will finish.
然後還有其他可以說的東西
讓我簡單解釋一下
讓我簡單解釋一下第一部分
剛剛問題是說
剛剛的流程基本上是一個線性流程
就是如果你要並行處理的話
怎麼樣可以讓 Jenkins 同時處理更多的 task 或是更多 job 這樣
如果只有一台電腦,它基本上就是跑一條線
做完一個動作之後,還會做下一個動作
不過,Jembex的好處是
你剛剛看到Stages的你要執行的內容
你可以自己去定義那裡面是要跑什麼
你可以在裡面某一個步驟,叫另外一台電腦幫你做測試
or you can ask another computer to build something for you and send it back later.
So if there are some parts of your build process that can be parallelized,
then you have more than one computer,
you can offload these operations to different computers.
Right, so Jacket has a few tools to make sure that you don't do concurrent builds
or that you don't do more than a build an hour or something.
You can configure that.
But really...
What we found is that we're doing this where instead of merging manually, we tell Jenkins to merge it and it's not building it, it's only running the unit tests.
And running the unit tests, if you pay a little bit of attention, you can make them run in under 10 minutes, even on a project of this scale.
And so if we can do it, I think...
this is something that should never clog up your build pipeline.
And then the builds, if they really take a long time,
just make one at the night.
At least you have run your unit tests every single time.
Like you are making some desktop application console game.
Like if you are making mobile game or mobile applications.
Like, do you also have some experience using the Jenkins to build it on Mac OS?
Like the different platforms?
To Android and iOS specifically?
Yeah, because, yeah, basically because for the, you can't build it from Windows for the iOS.
Right. Okay.
No, I've never built anything for mobile platforms.
We do have a similar problem for Linux and Mac, where we have to have a Mac computer to build for Mac and a Linux computer to build for Linux.
You can have all that in Jenkins, hooked up, and select which process runs on which machine.
I have no idea how long it takes or something to build something for Android.
Does it take a long time?
It depends how popular it is.
And if you build for different platforms, like different older platforms,
then we build several times.
Yeah, okay.
I said in the beginning we have a lot of platforms, right?
We have Windows, but Windows is really like lots of different stores, and so you have to make a build for each different store, because they all have their own store integration, DLL and stuff like that.
So, what we ended up doing is we build our experimental builds, we do it on Steam, because that's really easy, and then all the other stores, they only get the major releases.
So whenever we...
每個月我們會發佈一個穩定的更新
然後我們會為所有其他軟體做更新
因為他們沒有這種方便的軟體
好,那我很快就商量一下剛剛的問題
因為主要的問題是說
像在手機上你如果可能要預設很多不同的版本
或者是你可能是同一個平台
他就要針對不同OS版本去view不同內容之類的情況
可能你需要處理的版本數量很多
然後時間可能會很長
Jonas他提到的是
他們SmartMonitor也有發佈各種不同的PC平台版本
因為每個不同的PC平台都有一個平台的
整合的API,像Steam有Steamworks
Epic就Epic的其他東西
Windows Store有Windows Store的東西
如果是Control的話
Xbox、PlayStation有放自己的東西
這些版本全部都奧秘無錯
但是剛剛提到的很快速的測試
的行為
一個小時之內可以讓QA那邊收到他要的版本
原因是因為Steam有很方便的自動化上傳流程
而且包括可以讓測試人員跟任何外面公開的玩家
都可以直接用公開的版本
這是一個實驗版,但實驗是公開的,大家就自己來用就對了
因為Steam有這樣的功能
所以它才有辦法在PC上做一小時的翻譯時間
所以他們是每隔幾個禮拜或一個月
才會去發佈到其他的Controller或其他筆電平台上
但是Steam它就會有一個很快速的
比如說接近是Hourly的View這樣
每小時會有新版本出來
Right, and platforms like Xbox and Playstation, there's a manual step every time you want to release a build, they have certification and stuff.
So it would be impractical to try something like one hour turnaround time.
It's like days for those kind of platforms to push anything.
So we only do the big releases for them.
Cool.
So we'll just end the first session here and just go into open floor Q&A later.
Sure.
And if anyone is watching on Twitch, I'm happy to answer the questions there.
If there are any questions on Twitch, you can send them in at any time.
I'm using my own voice, so I won't be asking questions on the spot.
Let's see if people on Twitch can hear me.
I have a question. Was anyone able to connect to my computer?
有人可以聯絡他那個Server嗎?
那個Logos的8080
What's the IP?102.33
要上帝是不是?
對,要上帝
I don't think you want to give away password, right?
No
No way, right?
I can make a new user
It's on the demo project anyway
Oh wait, you mean the Windows password?
Not sure
No
Oh, there's a lock on screen, but we don't have the Jenkins password
OK, we'll do it after the workshop then
OK
Cool, thank you so much
好,那我們就先掌聲再謝謝四位
我們等一下時間大概還有一兩小時
我們就是現場有任何進階的問題
你要直接跟Travis討論的話
就是可以直接討論
那我自己是有準備一些問題
我等一下還是想要提出來
因為我想大家可能都會有點興趣聽說
到底可能還有些其他的
新手的問題或是新手狀況才會遇到
我們就先休息個二三十分鐘
等一下再繼續進行問題討論
有空餘的時間
大家想要展示東西
還是想要聊天
跟別人交流
這邊是隨意的
都可以用
上半場就先到這邊